Neil Ranada

User Experience Research & Design

Designer and veteran U.S. Navy pilot with over 10 years of professional experience in aviation, aerospace, and defense. I practice user-centered design backed by quantitative and qualitative research. I solve challenging problems by making mobile apps, websites, and other digital products easier to use so that people can focus on what matters most to them.

Experience

Freelance User Experience (UX) Researcher & Designer

Jan 2016 to Present

- Conduct iterative research, design, and testing to increase user control over map features in a mobile app
- Refine wireframes & mockups to streamline customer checkout process for a medical research fundraiser website
- Design content management prototype for usability testing to prove app features are recognizable and intuitive to use

Mission Planning Analyst

Apr 2014 to Dec 2015

- Mission Planning Analyst for the director of all U.S. Navy strategic assets in the Middle East
- Utilized specialized planning skills to advise leadership on options for allocating strategic assets each valued at \$1.5M+
- Conducted quality control for a successful \$3.4M test flight project for Raytheon
- Facilitated over 40 training events resulting in successful evaluation and certification

Aviation Safety Program Manager

May 2011 to Apr 2014

- Safety Program Manager for the director of all U.S. Navy helicopter assets throughout the Western U.S. and Pacific
- Oversaw safety programs for 13 aviation organizations consisting of 139 aircraft and over 3,600 personnel
- Advised executives on safety matters including hazards, mishaps, and system safety
- · Analyzed investigation reports and recommended corrective actions to address material and human causal factors
- · Reviewed and prioritized customer complaints, and collaborated with cross-functional teams to find timely solutions

Squadron Helicopter Pilot

Apr 2008 to Apr 2011

- Aircraft carrier based Helicopter Pilot leading crews in \$20M aircraft in search & rescue and disaster relief missions
- Led a small team solving complex logistics problems in a fast-paced, dynamic, multi-national environment
- Directed daily schedule to ensure completion of training and real-world flight operations

Education

M.A. International Relations – University of Oklahoma – Norman, OK

B.A. Geography - University of Washington - Seattle, WA

Arthur UX Workshops – Mapping Micro-Experiences, Digital Prototyping, Testing Designs with Users – San Diego, CA

Digital Telepathy Workshops – Essentials of Product Design, Essentials of Customer Interviews – San Diego, CA

Bloc, io – User Experience Design, User Interface Design, Front-end Development – Remote

Design Processes & Tools

Personas, User Stories & Flows, Wireframes, Mockups, Usability Testing, Prototype, Sketch App, InVision, Adobe XD